<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Paul Smith</title>
  <subtitle>Programmer, co-founder of EveryBlock</subtitle>
  <link href="http://pauladamsmith.com/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="http://pauladamsmith.com/" />
  <id>pauladamsmith.com</id>
  <updated>2010-10-31T19:07:05Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Paul Smith</name>
    <email>paulsmith@pobox.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>I know about old things</title>
    <link href="/blog/2010/10/old_things.html" />
    <id>http://pauladamsmith.com/blog/2010/10/old_things.html</id>
    <updated>2010-10-31T19:07:05Z</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post by Dave Winer is an example of an observation I’ve seen made
recently, which roughly goes, kids today, they didn’t grow up with
ringing-bell, handset-style telephones, or floppy disks, to name two
obsolete technologies, and so our icons for “call” and “save” in our
software don’t mean anything to them, because they don’t know what
those icons stand for (and by extension, what action is expected to
happen when you click on them). I think this overstates things. We
should always strive for better, more universally-understood metaphors
in our graphical interfaces, to make software easier to use and more
accessible. The idea that future kids won’t know about technologies
that had their heyday prior to their consciousness is belied by the
fact that I know about things before 1977, stuff like kerosene lamps,
telegraphs, and muskets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s set aside the fact that abstract graphical representations of
physical things, icons, tend to take on lives of their own, semantic
meanings that diverge from their real-world analogues (think folders,
files, and the desktop), so we don’t need to fully understand or even
be aware of the physical object to successfully use the virtual
one. (It’s not as if we had in-born knowledge of telephones and floppy
disks, and similarly we have to learn about software and its metaphors
in their own context.) In part because there is uneven deployment and
obsolescence of technology, in part because of cultural memory like
movies, and in part because of software and the Internet, we will
remember, and especially we will remember technologies that overlap,
in function or metaphor, and which are relevant to our contemporary
technology stories.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Héllö, Wòrld!</title>
    <link href="/blog/2010/10/hello_world.html" />
    <id>http://pauladamsmith.com/blog/2010/10/hello_world.html</id>
    <updated>2010-10-27T14:02:01Z</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a test of the emergency broadcast system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;codehilite&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kn&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nn&#34;&gt;antigravity&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;antigravity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Four score and seven years ago our fathers brought forth upon this continent a new nation …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¿I’m dining at “Café Foo”?&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>This is only a test</title>
    <link href="/blog/2010/10/this_is_only_a_test.html" />
    <id>http://pauladamsmith.com/blog/2010/10/this_is_only_a_test.html</id>
    <updated>2010-10-27T14:02:01Z</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now is the time for all good men to come to the aid of their party.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  </feed>